<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
       "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/uima_async_scaleout/async.errorhandling/" >
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.async.eh">
<title>Error Handling for Asynchronous Scaleout</title>
<para>This chapter discusses the high level architecture for Error Handling from the user's point of view. </para>
<section id="ugr.async.eh.basic">
<title>Basic concepts</title>
<para>This chapter describes error configuration for AS components.</para>
<para>The AS framework manages a collection of component parts written by users (user code) which can throw exceptions. In addition, the AS framework can run timers when sending commands to user code which can create timeouts.</para>
<para>An AS component is either an AS aggregate or an AS primitive. AS aggregates can have multiple levels of aggregation; error configuration is done for each level of aggregation. The rest of this chapter focuses on the error configuration one level at a time (either for one particular level in an aggregate hierarchy, or for an AS primitive). </para>
<para>There is a small number of commands which can be sent to an AS component. When a component returns the result, if an error occurs, an error result is returned instead of the normal result.</para>
<para>Configuration and support is provided for three classes of errors: </para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Exceptions thrown from code (component or framework) at this level</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>error messages received from delegates.</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>timeouts of commands sent to delegates.</para></listitem></orderedlist>
<para>The second and third class of errors is only possible for AS aggregates.</para>
<para>When errors happen, the framework provides a standard set of configurable actions. See 
<xref linkend="ugr.async.eh.commands_allowed_actions"></xref> for a summary table of the actions available in different situations.</para></section>
<section id="ugr.async.eh.incoming_commands">
<title>Associating Errors with incoming commands</title>
<para>Components managed by AS may generate errors when they are sent a command. The error is associated with the command that was running to produce the error. </para>
<!--figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.message_commands">
    <title>Commands contained in messages</title>
    <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
    <imagedata width="350px" format="JPG"
    fileref="&imgroot;message_commands.jpg"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><phrase>Commands contained in messages</phrase>
    </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure-->
<para>There are three incoming message commands supported by the AS framework: 
<orderedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>getMetadata - sent by the framework when initializing connection to an AS component</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>processCas - sent once for each CAS</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>collectionProcessComplete - sent when an application calls this method</para></listitem>
<!--listitem><para>terminate - stop running and clean up; sent by the framework as part
          of a terminate action</para></listitem--></orderedlist> </para>
<!--itemizedlist mark="none"><listitem><para>There are three other commands, but
    these are not passed as messages:
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem><para>initialize (called by the framework when creating an instance
    of the component)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>reinitialize</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>terminate</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist> </para></listitem>
    
    </itemizedlist-->
<para>Error handling actions are associated with these various commands. 
  Some error handling actions make sense only if there is an associated CAS object, 
  and are therefore only allowed with the processCas command. </para></section>
<section id="ugr.async.eh.error_handling_overview">
<title>Error handling overview</title>
<para>When an error happens, it is either &quot;recovered&quot;, or not; 
  only errors from delegates of an AS aggregate can be recovered. 
  Recovery may be achieved by retrying the request or by skipping the delegate.</para>
<para>Commands normally return results; however if an non-recoverable error occurs, the command returns an error result instead. </para>
<para>For AS aggregates, each level in aggregate hierarchy can be configured to try to recover the error. If a
  particular AS aggregate level does not recover, the error is sent up to the next level of the hierarchy (or to the
  calling client, if a top level). 
  The error result is updated to reflect the actions the framework takes for this
  error. </para>
<para>Non-recovered errors can optionally have an associated &quot;Terminate&quot; or 
  &quot;Disable&quot; action (see below), triggered by the error when a threshold is reached. 
  "Disable" applies to the delegate that generated the error while "Terminate" applies to the 
  aggregate and any co-located aggregates it is contained within.</para>
  
<figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.basic_eh_chain">
<title>Basic error handling chain for AS Aggregates for errors from delegates</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata width="324px" format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;error_chain_aggr.png"></imagedata>
  </imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Basic error handling chain for aggregates</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure>
  
<para>The basic error handling chain starts with an error, and can attempt to recover using retry. 
  If this fails (or is not configured), the error count is incremented and checked against the thresholds for this delegate.  If the threshold has been reached the specified action is taken, disabling the delegate or terminating the entire component. If the Terminate error is not taken, recovery by the Continue action can be attempted. If that fails, an error result is returned to the caller. </para>
<para>For AS primitives, only the Terminate action is available, and Retry and Continue do not apply.</para>

  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.basic_eh_chain_prim">
<title>Basic error handling chain for AS Primitives</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata width="241px" format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;error_chain_prim.png"></imagedata>
  </imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Basic error handling chain for aggregates</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure>

  
</section>

<section id="ugr.async.eh.error_results">
<title>Error results</title>
<para>Error results are returned instead of a CAS, if an error occurs and is not recovered.</para>
<para>If the application uses the synchronous sendAndReceive() method, an Error Result is passed back to the client API.  The particular exception varies, depending on many factors, but will include a complete stack trace beginning with the cause of the error.  If the application uses an asynchronous API, the exception is wrapped in a EntityProcessStatus object and delivered via a callback listener registered by the application. See section 4.4 Status Callback Listener for details.</para>
</section>

<section id="ugr.async.eh.aggregate_managed">
<title>Error Recovery actions</title>
<para>When errors occur in delegates, the aggregate containing them can attempt to recover. There are two basic recovery actions: retrying the same command and continuing past (skipping) the failing component. </para>
<!--para>Errors associated with a delegate are either exceptions or timeouts.</para>
    
    <para>An aggregate receives exceptions thrown by a delegate as a message being
    returned from that delegate, in place of the normal return message.
    Normal execution returns a CAS if the command was "processCas"; but if an
    exception is returned, the CAS is not sent back. </para>
    <note><para>If the delegate is co-located, the
    aggregate and the delegate are actually sharing a common CAS object, so the
    aggregate has access to the CAS in this case.</para></note-->
<para>Every command sent to a delegate can have an associated (configurable) timeout. If the timeout occurs before the delegate responds, the framework creates an error representing the timeout. 
<note>
<para>If, subsequently, a response is (finally) received corresponding to the command that had timed-out, this is logged, but the response is discarded and no further action is taken.</para></note> </para>
<!--figure
      id="ugr.async.eh.fig.error_chain_aggregate_without_terminate_disable">
      <title>Retry chain</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="170px" format="JPG"
            fileref="&imgroot;error_chain_aggregate_without_terminate_disable.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Error handling - aggregate</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure-->
<para>When errors occur in delegates, retry is attempted (if configured), some number of times. If that fails, error counts are incremented and thresholds examined for Terminate/Disable actions. If not reached, or if the action is Disable, Continue is attempted (if configured); if Continue fails, the error is not recovered, and the aggregate returns the error result from the delegate to the aggregate's caller. On Terminate, the error is returned to the caller.</para>

<section id="ugr.async.eh.aggregate_managed.actions">
<title>Aggregate Error Actions</title>
<para>This section describes in more detail the error actions valid only for AS aggregates.</para>
<section id="ugr.async.eh.aggregate_managed.actions.retry">
<title>Retry</title>
<para>Retry is an action which re-sends the same command that failed back to the input queue of the delegate. (Note: It may be picked up by a different instance of that delegate, which may have a better chance of succeeding.) The framework will keep a copy of the CAS sent to remote components in order to have it to send again if a retry is required.</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Retry is not allowed for colocated delegates.</emphasis></para>
<para>The &quot;collectionProcessComplete&quot; command is never retried.</para>
<para>Retry is done some number of times, as specified in the deployment descriptor.</para></section>
<!-- end of retry -->
<section id="ugr.async.eh.aggregate_disable">
<title>Disable Action</title>
<figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.disable">
<title>Disable action</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata width="150px" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;disable_action.jpg"></imagedata></imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Disable Action</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure>
<para>When this action is taken the framework marks the particular delegate causing the error as &quot;disabled&quot; so it will be skipped in subsequent calls. The framework calls the flow controller, telling it to remove the particular delegate from the flow.</para></section>
<section id="ugr.async.eh.aggregate_managed.actions.continue">
<title>Continue Option on Delegate Process CAS Failures</title>
<para>For processCas commands, the Continue action causes the framework to give the flow controller object for that CAS the error details, and ask the flow controller if processing can continue. If the flow controller returns &quot;true&quot;, the flow controller will be called asking for the next step; if &quot;false&quot;, the framework stops processing the CAS, returning an error to the client reply queue, or just returning the CAS to the casPool of the CAS multiplier which created it. </para>
<para>For &quot;collectionProcessComplete&quot; commands, Continue means to ignore the error, and continue as if the collectionProcessComplete call had returned normally.</para>
<para>This action is not allowed for the getMetadata command.</para></section>
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.aggregate_managed.actions.abort_cas">
      <title>AbortCas Action</title>
      <para>AbortCas means that, at this level in the aggregate nesting,
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem><para>further CAS processing stops</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>the underlying error result is return, with an indication that
      CAS processing was aborted.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist> </para>
      
      <para>AbortCas is only allowed for the processCas command; the other commands do not have
      an associated CAS.</para>
      </section--></section>
<!-- end of aggregate_managed.actions --></section>
<!-- end of aggregate_managed -->
<!--para>The Terminate looking "upwards" towards its caller, disconnects the component (where the error is being handled) 
    from its input queue; while the Disable, looking "downwards" toward a particular delegate, removes that delegate
    from the list of delegates its flow controller will send work to.
    </para-->
<!--figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.terminate_disable">
    <title>Terminate and Disable actions</title>
    <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
    <imagedata width="250px" format="JPG"
    fileref="&imgroot;terminate_disable.jpg"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><phrase>Terminate and Disable Actions</phrase>
    </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure-->
<section id="ugr.async.eh.errors_passed_up.thresholds">
<title>Thresholds for Terminate and Disable</title>
<para>The Terminate and Disable actions are conditioned by testing against a threshold.</para>
<para>Thresholds are specified as two numbers - an error count and a window. The threshold is reached if the number of errors occurring within the window size is equal to or greater than &quot;the error count&quot;. A value of 0 disables the error threshold so no action can be taken. A window of 0 means no window, i.e. all errors are counted.</para>
<para>Errors associated with the processCas command are the only ones that are counted in the threshold measurements.</para></section>
<section id="ugr.async.eh.terminate">
<title>Terminate Action</title>
<para>When this action is taken the service represented by this component sends an error reply and then terminates, disconnecting itself as a listener from its input queue, and cleaning itself up (releasing resources, etc.). During cleanup, the component analysis engine's 
<literal>destroy</literal> method is called.</para>

<note><para>The termination action applies to the entire aggregate service. Remote delegates are not affected.</para></note>

<figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.terminate">
<title>Terminate action</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata width="150px" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;terminate_action.jpg"></imagedata></imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Terminate Action</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure>
<para>If the threshold is not exceeded, the error counts associated with the threshold are incremented.</para>
<note>
<para>Some errors will always cause a terminate: for instance, framework or flow controller errors cause immediate termination.</para></note></section>
<!-- end of actions for terminate -->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.error_wrapping">
  <title>Error wrapping</title>
  <para>An error occurring at some level will be wrapped by other errors as it is passed up the chain.
  The wrapping mechanism used is the standard Java one (since Java 1.4).  The wrapping preserves the
  original error while adding information about how it was handled at higher levels.</para>
  </section-->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.error_chaining">
  <title>Error chaining</title>
  <para>Once an error occurs, it may result in several different actions happening
  as the error is passed through a chain of error handlers.  There are four possible situations,
  each having a particular chain configuration:
  
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>AS aggregate</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>AS primitive having a remote service client connecting to an AS service</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Synchronous component having a remote service client connecting to an AS service</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>AS primitive without a service client descriptor connecting to an AS service
  </para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </para>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.error_chaining.as-aggregate">
  <title>AS aggregate error chaining</title>
  <para> For an AS aggregate, the actions are chained together as follows:
  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.error_chain_aggregate_without_terminate_disable">
  <title>Retry chain</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata width="170px" format="JPG"
  fileref="&imgroot;error_chain_aggregate_without_terminate_disable.jpg"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>Error handling - aggregate</phrase>
  </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>First, retry is attempted, if it's enabled, and the retry
  count has not been exceeded.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Second, recovery by Continuing is attempted, if
  specified.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>If neither of these two strategies succeeds, a AbortCas error, 
  wrapping the error being handled, will be sent
  back as a reply to the command associated with the error, in place of the CAS.</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist> </para>
  
  <para>In the figure, the upwards pointing arrows show the next error handler in the chain.  If
  the "Retry" or "Continue" action succeeds, no error is reported up higher.</para>
  
  <para>When an error is sent back as a reply from the aggregate, if the Disable and/or
  Terminate actions have been configured for this aggregate, the error counts are
  checked against the threshold, and if the threshold is passed, the Disable or Terminate
  action occurs as the error is sent up, and the error is again wrapped, indicating this.</para>
  
  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.error_chain_aggregate">
  <title>Error chain - aggregate</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata width="230px" format="JPG"
  fileref="&imgroot;error_chain_aggregate.jpg"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>Error handling - in an aggregate</phrase>
  </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.error_chaining.as_primitive_or_synchronous_as_remote">
  <title>AS primitive and synchronous with AS remote: error chaining</title>
  <para>AS primitive or synchronous components having AS remote service clients 
  have an error chain for each of those remotes, similar
  to normal AS-managed aggregates, except that there is no "Continue" action (because
  there is no flow controller involved), and the
  "Terminate" action is allowed only for AS primitive components (it is not allowed
  for synchronous ones).
  </para>  
  
  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.error_as_primitive_with_AS_remote">
  <title>Error chain for AS primitive or synchronous components having AS remotes</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata width="150px" format="JPG"
  fileref="&imgroot;error_primitive_with_AS_remote.jpg"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>Error handling - AS primitive or synchronous components having AS remotes</phrase>
  </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.error_chaining.as_primitive_without_as_remote">
  <title>AS primitive without AS remote: error chaining</title>
  <para>AS primitive components not containing AS remote service clients can only specify a Terminate action for exceptions
  thrown in the component.</para>  
  
  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.error_primitive">
  <title>Terminate action for AS Primitive Components without AS remote service clients</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata width="230px" format="JPG"
  fileref="&imgroot;error_primitive.jpg"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>Error handling - AS primitive components without AS remote service clients only support Terminate</phrase>
  </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  </section>
  
  </section-->
<section id="ugr.async.eh.commands_allowed_actions">
<title>Commands and allowed actions</title>
<para>All of the allowed actions are optional, and default to not being done, except for getMetadata being sent to a delegate that is remote - this has a default timeout of 1 minute.</para>
<para>Here's a table of the allowed actions, by command. In this table, the Retry, Continue, and Disable actions apply to the particular Delegate associated with the error; the Terminate action applies to the entire component. </para>
<para>The framework returns an Error Result to the caller for errors that are not recovered.</para>
<table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="ugr.async.eh.table.error_actions_by_command">
<title>Error actions by command type</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"></colspec>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"></colspec>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="2*"></colspec>
<thead>
<row>
<entry morerows="1" valign="middle">Command</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col3" align="center">Error actions allowed</entry></row>
<row>
<entry colname="col2">AS Aggregate</entry>
<entry>AS Primitive</entry></row></thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>getMetadata</entry>
<entry>Retry, Disable, Terminate</entry>
<entry>Terminate</entry></row>
<row>
<entry>processCas</entry>
<entry>Retry, Continue, Disable, Terminate</entry>
<entry>Terminate</entry></row>
<row>
<entry>collection Processing Complete</entry>
<entry>Continue, Disable, Terminate</entry>
<entry>Terminate</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
<para>The rationale for providing the terminate action for primitive services is that only the service can know that it is no longer capable of continued operation. Consider a scaled component with multiple service instances, where one of them goes &quot;bad&quot; and starts throwing exceptions: the clients of this service have no way of stopping new requests from being delivered to this bad service instance. The teminate action allows the bad service to remove itself from further processing, and even allow life cycle management to restart a new instance.</para>
</section>

<!--
  There are predefined error conditions, and predefined actions that can be taken for
  these.</para>
  
  <para>Aggregate components specify error handling for each of their delegates. Error
  Handling is configured using the Deployment Descriptor &lt;errorConfiguration>
  element. This element associates a specification with each delegate of an aggregate.
  </para>
  
  <para>In addition, any AS component can specify a &lt;terminate> element, specifying that
  the component should disconnect from its input queue and return a "terminate" message,
  once a specified threshold is reached. The threshold is frequency and/or absolute count
  based.</para>
  
  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.eh_done_1_higher">
  <title>Error Handling using specs from delegates</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata width="400px" format="PNG"
  fileref="&imgroot;eh_done_1_higher.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>Error Handling using specs from delegates</phrase>
  </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <para>The deployment descriptor configures error handling; it can be configured at each
  level of a nested aggregate hierarchy. An &lt;errorConfiguration> element contained in
  a &lt;delegate> element specifies error handling configuration for the containing
  aggregate. A special &lt;terminate> element specifies termination behavior for the
  component it is contained in.</para>
  
  <para>Error handling is always (with the exception of Terminate, described later) done one
  level up from the component that produced the error (in other words, in the containing
  aggregate, if there is one, or in the client if there is no containing aggregate). </para>
  
  <para>There are two classes of errors: time-out errors and exception errors.</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>When an AS component receives a CAS to work on, it either returns that CAS (no error
  case), or it returns the error (typically (in Java) a serialized version of a
  "throwable" object), instead of a CAS.</para></listitem>
  <listitem>
  
  <para>Timeout errors are generated, not at the delegate, but at the aggregate which
  sent a request for some kind of processing and timed-out waiting for the
  response.</para>
  
  <para>When timeout errors happen, the delegate may at some later time actually
  complete the request send the reply message, or it may send an exception error. In both
  cases, after a time out has occurred, these messages are discarded.</para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.chains">
  <title>Error handling chains</title>
  
  <figure id="ugr.async.eh.fig.basic_chain">
  <title>Error Handling chain sequence</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata width="150px" format="PNG"
  fileref="&imgroot;basic_chain.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>Error Handling chain sequence</phrase>
  </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <para> Error handling is done in a chain, as follows. </para>
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>If Terminate or Disable action has been specified, the error is
  counted, and tested to see if the threshold / frequency has been exceeded. If not, the
  error is passed to the next part of the chain.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>If the error is one where a retry operation is enabled, and the
  threshold has not been exceeded, a retry is done.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Otherwise, the specified action is done.</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.thresholds_frequencies">
  <title>Thresholds and Frequencies</title>
  <para>The configuration includes specification of thresholds and frequencies. These
  are used to control when certain actions are taken.</para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Thresholds</emphasis> imply an implicit retry (if
  retry is possible) up to the number of times indicated in the threshold. Retry is
  only possible if the aggregate kept a copy of the original CAS when sending it for
  processing to the delegate which subsequently produced the error. In the
  deployment descriptor, this is controlled using the
  &lt;casManagement enableRevert="true | false"/> element in the
  &lt;errorConfiguration> element. </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>Frequencies specify an error "rate" - expressed as two numbers. The first is
  the number of errors, the second is a number of CASes processed ("NumberOfCASes").
  The frequency is exceeded if there are greater than the number of errors in a
  consecutive set of "NumberOfCASes" CASes.</para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <!- section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.action_directions">
  <title>Action Directions</title>
  <para>In a general aggregate analysis engine, actions can be directed "upwards"
  toward the containing aggregate (if there is one) or "downwards" toward one (or more)
  of the delegate(s).</para>
  </section-->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.action_types">
  <title>Available Actions</title>
  <para>All error handling routines tell the framework to take one of several possible
  actions. The set of actions available depends on the context of the error; the context
  includes the following: </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
  <listitem>
  <para>Does this component have delegates being managed by AS?</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>Is this component co-located with its containing aggregate (if it has a
  containing aggregate)? </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Is this component's delegate co-located?</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Was the &lt;casManagement> element configured to enable CAS
  reversion (returning the CAS to the state it was before it was sent to the delegate
  which raised the error condition)?</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Did the request which resulted in the error being received have an
  associated CAS being managed in a flow?</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>Actions available include: Terminate, Disable, Continue, and DropCas.</para>
  
  <para>The {Terminate, Disable} actions are considered first. If not applicable, the
  other actions are considered. </para>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.action_types.terminate">
  <title>Terminate action</title>
  
  <para>Only one of {Terminate, Disable} can be specified; Terminate is associated with
  the component where the &lt;errorConfiguration> element is. It is the only action
  that is allowed for a top-level component of a service, and for non-AS components
  (primitives and async="no" aggregates)</para>
  
  <para>Enabled: always</para>
  
  <para>Threshold/Frequency: if not met, increment the monitoring counters, and
  Otherwise, do the action.</para>
  
  <para>Effect: the service removes itself as a listener on its input queue, "cleans up"
  any resources it can, and shuts down. For services containing co-located delegates,
  the cleanup and shut down process is propagated to all local delegates. (In this
  version, we required local, co-located delegates to be non-shared.)</para>
  
  <para>An example: consider an aggregate having several components, one of which is
  "critical". If the critical component fails, the deployer can decide to terminate
  the entire aggregate service.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.action_types.disable">
  <title>Disable action</title>
  
  <para>Only one of {Terminate, Disable} can be specified; Disable is a specific to one
  delegate of an aggregate</para>
  
  <para>Enabled: always</para>
  
  <para>Threshold/Frequency: if not met, increment the monitoring counters, and
  Otherwise, do the action.</para>
  
  <para>Effect: for this (if a CAS exists for this request) and all subsequent CASes in a
  run, override the flow controller and "skip" any requests to send a CAS to that
  component.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.action_types.continue">
  <title>Continue action</title>
  
  <para>Enabled: only for requests to delegates passing a CAS and when
  &lt;casManagement enableRevert="true"/> is configured for this delegate</para>
  
  <para>Threshold: if not met, and &lt;casManagement enableRevert="true"/>, retry
  the operation on the component using the reverted CAS, and increment the retry count.
  Otherwise, do the action.</para>
  
  <para>Effect: causes the framework to send the CAS to the flow controller, asking it to
  continue to the next delegate. The flow controller can decline to do this in this case
  (it is told that the previous component signalled an error), and if so, the Continue is
  converted to a DropCas action. <emphasis role="review">This action is not
  permitted for CAS Multipliers.</emphasis> </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.async.eh.basic.action_types.drop_cas">
  <title>Drop Cas action</title>
  
  <para>Enabled: only for requests to delegates passing a CAS</para>
  
  <para>Threshold: if not met, and &lt;casManagement enableRevert="true"/>, retry
  the operation on the component using the reverted CAS, and increment the retry count.
  Otherwise, do the action.</para>
  
  <para>Effect: causes the framework to return the Cas to the Cas Pool, and return a
  "DropCas" exception to its caller. </para>
  </section>
  </section> <!- - action_types - ->
  
  </section> <!- - basic -->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.callbacks">
  <title>Considerations for call-back routines</title>
  <para> Error handling supports the following callbacks: </para>
  
  <para> Call back routines are configured by: </para>
  
  <para> For each call back routine: when it is called, what it is passed, what it can do.
  </para>
  
  </section-->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.cas_multipliers">
  <title>Considerations for Cas Multipliers</title>
  <para>tbd</para>
  </section-->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.defaulting">
  <title>Error Handling defaults and inheritance</title>
  <para>tbd</para>
  </section-->
<!--section id="ugr.async.eh.error_context">
  <title>Error Contexts</title>
  <para>An Error Context is created for each error and passed to error handling methods. It
  contains the following:
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
  <listitem><para>The command instigating the action</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>The exception (if there is one)</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>A flag indicating timeout (if it is a timeout)</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>(aggregate-detected errors only) The delegate key</para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist> </para>
  </section--></chapter>
