<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY sisterProject "../../../../uima-docbooks/src/docbook/">
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../../uima-docbook-tool/xinclude.mod">
  %xinclude;
  ]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<book lang="en">
  <title>UIMA Asynchronous Scaleout</title>
  <!--
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="&sisterProject;/common_book_info.xml"/>

  <toc/>
  -->  
  <bookinfo>
    <releaseinfo>Release 0.6</releaseinfo> <productname>UIMA AS</productname>
    <legalnotice>
      <para> </para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Notices</title>
        <para>This information was developed for products and services offered in the
          U.S.A. IBM may not offer the products, services, or features discussed in this
          document in other countries. Consult your local IBM representative for
          information on the products and services currently available in your area. Any
          reference to an IBM product, program, or service is not intended to state or imply
          that only that IBM product, program, or service may be used. Any functionally
          equivalent product, program, or service that does not infringe any IBM
          intellectual property right may be used instead. However, it is the user’s
          responsibility to evaluate and verify the operation of any non-IBM product,
          program, or service. </para> </formalpara>
      
      <para>IBM may have patents or pending patent applications covering subject matter
        described in this document. The furnishing of this document does not give you any
        license to these patents. You can send license inquiries, in writing, to:</para>
      <programlisting>IBM Director of Licensing 
IBM Corporation 
North Castle Drive 
Armonk, NY
10504-1785 U.S.A. </programlisting>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"> The following paragraph does not apply to the United
        Kingdom or any other country where such provisions are inconsistent with local
        law:</emphasis> INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES CORPORATION PROVIDES THIS
        PUBLICATION "AS IS" WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESS OR IMPLIED,
        INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF NON-INFRINGEMENT,
        MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. Some states do not allow
        disclaimer of express or implied warranties in certain transactions, therefore,
        this statement may not apply to you. </para>
      <para> This information could include technical inaccuracies or typographical
        errors. Changes are periodically made to the information herein; these changes will
        be incorporated in new editions of the publication. IBM may make improvements and/or
        changes in the product(s) and/or the program(s) described in this publication at any
        time without notice. </para>
      <para>Information concerning non-IBM products was obtained from the suppliers of
        those products, their published announcements or other publicly available
        sources. IBM has not tested those products and cannot confirm the accuracy of
        performance, compatibility or any other claims related to non-IBM products.
        Questions on the capabilities of non-IBM products should be addressed to the
        suppliers of those products.</para>
      <para> All statements regarding IBM’s future direction or intent are subject to change
        or withdrawal without notice, and represent goals and objectives only. </para>
      
      <formalpara>
        <title>Trademarks</title>
        <para> The following terms are trademarks of the IBM Corporation in the United
          States, other countries, or both. </para></formalpara><para> IBM </para>
      <para> The following terms are trademarks or registered trademarks of other
      companies: </para><para> Microsoft, Windows, Windows NT, and the Windows logo are
      trademarks of Microsoft Corporation in the United States, other countries, or both.
      </para><para> Java and all Java-based trademarks are trademarks of Sun Microsystems,
      Inc. in the United States, other countries, or both. </para><para> Eclipse is a
      trademark of Eclipse Foundation, Inc. </para>
      <para>All terms mentioned in the text that are known to be trademarks or service marks
        have been appropriately capitalized. Use of such terms in this book should not be
        regarded as affecting the validity of the the trademark or service mark. </para>
      
      <para> </para>
      <para> </para>
      <para> </para>
      <para>This edition applies to the IBM Unstructured information Management
        Architecture Asynchronous Scaleout Edition (UIMA AS) Version 0.5.0 and to all subsequent
        release and modifications until otherwise indicated in new editions.</para>
      <para>US Government Users Restricted Rights - Use, duplication or disclosure
        restricted by GSA ADP Schedule Contract with IBM Corp.</para>
    </legalnotice>
    <copyright>
      <year>2007</year>
      <holder>International Business Machines Corporation.  All rights reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <pubdate>August, 2007</pubdate>
    
  </bookinfo>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="async.overview.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="async.errorhandling.xml"/> 
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="ref.async.deployment.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="ref.async.api.xml" />

  <!--
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="async.tutorial.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="async.reference.xml"/>
  -->
</book>
