<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY sisterProject "../../../../uima-docbooks/src/docbook/">
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/uima_async_scaleout/async.overview/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../../../../uima-docbooks/src/docbook/entities.ent" >
  %uimaents;
  ]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
  
<chapter id="ugr.ref.async.api">
  <title>Asynchronous Scaleout Application Interface</title>
  
  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.organization">
    <title>Asynchonous API Overview</title>
    <para>
      The Asynchronous API provides Java applications the capability to connect to
      and to make reqests UIMA EE services. ProcessCas and CollectionProcessingComplete
      requests are supported.
    </para>

    <para>
      An application can prepare and send each CAS to a service one at a time, or
      alternately can use a UIMA collection reader to prepare the CASes to be delivered.
      The application must provide a listener class to receive asynchronous replies.
      For individual CAS requests a synchronous sendAndReceive call is available. 
      Note that for synchronous requests to a
      UIMA EE service, the standard UIMA Analysis Engine APIs
      can be used with an analysis engine instantiated from a JMS Service Descriptor.
      See <xref linkend="ugr.async.ov.concepts.jms_descriptor"/>.
    </para>

     <para>
      Other options include specifying the maximum number of outstanding requests allowed, timeout
      values and the size of local Cas pool to create.      
     </para>
    
    <para>
      The Asynchronous API can also be used to deploy services.
      Java services deployed by the API are instantiated in the same JVM. Logging for all UIMA
      components in the same JVM are merged; class names and thread IDs can be used to distinguish
      log entries from different services. All services in the JVM can be monitored by a single
      JMX console. Native (org.apache.uima.cpp) services can be called from the JVM via the JNI or
      optionally be launched as separate processes on the same machine. In either case logging
      and JMX monitoring for native services are integrated with the those in the JVM.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
    <!--======================================================-->    
    <!--        UimaAsynchronousEngine interface              -->    
    <!--======================================================-->    
  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.descriptor">
    <title>The UimaAsynchronousEngine Interface</title>
    
    <para>An application developer's starting point for accessing UIMA EE services is the
      UimaAsynchronousEngine Interface. For each service an application wants to use, it
      must instantiate a client object:

      <programlisting>UimaAsynchronousEngine uimaAsEngine = 
        new BaseUIMAAsynchronousEngine_impl();</programlisting>

      The following is a short introduction to some important methods on this class.
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>void initialize( Map anApplicationContext ): Initializes asynchronous client. 
            Using configuration provided in a given Map object, this method creates a connection to 
            UIMA EE Service queue, creates a response queue, and retrieves service metadata. 
            This method blocks until a reply is received from the service or a timeout occurs.
            If a collection reader has been specified, it's typesystem is merged with that from the
            service. The combined typesystem is used to create a Cas pool.
            On success the application is notified via the listener's initializationComplete() method.
            Asynchronous errors are delivered to the listener's entityProcessComplete() method.
            See <xref linkend="ugr.ref.async.context.map"/> for more about the ApplicationContext map.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void addStatusCallbackListener(StatusCallbackListener aListener):
            Plugs-in application specific listener. The application receives callbacks
            via methods in this listener class. More than one listener can be added.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CAS getCAS(): Requests a new CAS instance from the CAS pool. This method blocks
            until a free instance of CAS is available in the CAS pool.
            Applications that use getCAS() need to call CAS.reset() as appropriate or CAS.release()
            to return it to the Cas pool.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void sendCAS( CAS aCAS ): Sends a given CAS for analysis to UIMA EE Service. 
            This method may block if the client is configured to use a reply window which prevents 
            from sending too many CASes to the service. Assuming the window is large enough to send 
            the CAS this method returns as soon as the CAS is sent.
            The application is notified of responses or timeouts via entityProcessComplete().
         </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void setCollectionReader( CollectionReader aCollectionReader ): 
            Plugs in an instantiated CollectionReader instance to use. Must be called before initialize.
            The application calls the process() method to begin analyzing the collection.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void process(): 
           Starts processing a collection using a collection reader. The method will block
           until the CollectionReader finishes processing the entire collection.  
           Throws ResourceProcessException if a CollectionReader has not been provided or initialize
           has not been called.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void collectionProcessingComplete(): Sends a Collection Processing Complete request 
            to UIMA EE Analysis Service. The method blocks until the service replies or a timeout occurs.
            On success the application is notified via the listener's initializationComplete() method.
            Asynchronous errors are delivered to the listener's entityProcessComplete() method.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void sendAndReceiveCAS(CAS aCAS):
            Send a CAS, wait for response. On success aCAS contains the analysis results.
            Errors are delivered to the listener's entityProcessComplete() method.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>String deploy( String aDeploymentDescriptor, Map anApplicationContext):
            Deploys UIMA EE service specified by given deployment descriptor and returns a handle
            to the Spring container for this service.
            The application context map must contain DD2SpringXsltFilePath and SaxonClasspath entries.
            This call blocks until the service is ready to process requests, or an exception occurs
            during deployment.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void undeploy( String aSpringContainerId ):
            Tells the specified service to terminate and removes the Spring container.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void stop():
           Stops the asynchronous client. Removes Cas pool, drops connection to the UIMA EE
           service queue and stops listening on it's response queue. 
           Also, terminates and undeploys any services which have been started with this client.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist></para>

    </section>


    <!--======================================================-->    
    <!--         Application Context Map                      -->    
    <!--======================================================-->    
    <section id="ugr.ref.async.context.map">
      <title>Application Context Map</title>
      <para>The application context map is used to pass initialization parameters.
        These parameters are itemized below.

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>DD2SpringXsltFilePath: Required for deploying services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SaxonClasspath: Required for deploying services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ServerURI: Broker connector for service. Required for initialize.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Endpoint: Service queue name. Required for initialize.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CasPoolSize: Size of Cas pool to create to send to specified service. Default = 1.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ReplyWindow: Maximum number of outstanding process CAS requests that can be sent.
            Default = 5.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Timeout: Process CAS timeout in ms. Default = no timeout.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>GetMetaTimeout: Initialize timeout in ms. Default = 60 seconds.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CpcTimeout: Collection process complete timeout. Default = no timeout.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist></para>

  </section>


    <!--======================================================-->    
    <!--         Status Callback Listener                     -->    
    <!--======================================================-->    
    <section id="ugr.ref.async.callback.listener">
      <title>Status Callback Listener</title>
      <para>Asynchronous events are delivered to applications via methods in classes registered
          to the API object with addStatusCallbackListener(). These classes must implement the
          interface org.apache.uima.aae.client.UimaAsStatusCallbackListener.

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>initializationComplete(EntityProcessStatus aStatus): The callback used to inform the
            application that the initialization request has completed. On success aStatus will be
            null; on failure use the EntityProcessStatus class to get the details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>entityProcessComplete(CAS aCas, EntityProcessStatus aStatus): The callback used to 
            inform the application that a processCas request has completed. On success aStatus 
            will be null; on failure use the EntityProcessStatus class to get the details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>collectionProcessComplete(EntityProcessStatus aStatus): The callback used to inform the
            application that the CPC request has completed. On success aStatus will be
            null; on failure use the EntityProcessStatus class to get the details.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
  </section>


    <!--======================================================-->    
    <!--         Error Results                                -->    
    <!--======================================================-->    
    <section id="ugr.ref.async.error.status">
      <title>Error Results</title>
      <para>Errors are delivered to the callback listeners as an EntityProcessStatus object.
          
        <note><para>The use of EntityProcessStatus is temporary. This will be replaced shortly.
        </para></note>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>isException(): Indicates the error returned is in the form of exception messages.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>getExceptions(): Returns a List of exceptions.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.usage">
    <title>Asynchonous API Usage Scenarios</title>

  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.usage_initialize">
    <title>Instantiating a Client API Object</title>
    <para>
      A client API object must be instantiated for each remote service an application will 
      directly connect with, and a listener class registered in order to process asynchronous events:
        <programlisting>//create Asynchronous Client API
uimaAsEngine = new BaseUIMAAsynchronousEngine_impl();
uimaAsEngine.addStatusCallbackListener(new MyStatusCallbackListener());
    </programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.usage_callservice">
    <title>Calling an Existing Service</title>
    <para>
      The following code shows how to establish connection to an existing service:
        <programlisting>//create Map to pass server URI and Endpoint parameters
Map&lt;String,Object&gt; appCtx = new HashMap&lt;String,Object&gt;();
// Add Broker URI on local machine
appCtx.put(UimaAsynchronousEngine.ServerUri, "tcp://localhost:61616");
// Add Queue Name
appCtx.put(UimaAsynchronousEngine.Endpoint, "RoomNumberAnnotatorQueue");
// Add the Cas Pool Size
appCtx.put(UimaAsynchronousEngine.CasPoolSize, 2);

//initialize
uimaAsEngine.initialize(appCtx);
    </programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Prepare a Cas and send it to the service:
    <programlisting>//get an empty CAS from the Cas pool
CAS cas = uimaAsEngine.getCAS();
// Initialize it with input data
cas.setDocumentText("Some text to pass to this service.");
// Send Cas to service for processing
uimaAsEngine.sendCAS(cas);
    </programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.usage_getresults">
    <title>Retrieving Asynchonous Results</title>
    <para>
      Asynchronous events resulting from the process Cas request are passed to the registered listener.
        <programlisting>
// Callback Listener. Receives event notifications from CPE.
class MyStatusCallbackListener implements StatusCallbackListener {

// Method called when the processing of a Document is completed.
public void entityProcessComplete(CAS aCas, EntityProcessStatus aStatus) {
  if (aStatus != null &amp;&amp; aStatus.isException()) {
    List exceptions = aStatus.getExceptions();
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; exceptions.size(); i++) {
      ((Throwable) exceptions.get(i)).printStackTrace();
      }
    uimaAsEngine.stop();
    return;
    }

// Process the retrieved Cas here
// ...
  }

// Add other required callback methods below...
}
    </programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.usage_deployservice">
    <title>Deploying a Service with the Client API</title>
    <para>
      Services can be deployed from a client object independently of any service connection.
      The main motivation for this feature is to be able to deploy a service, connect to it, and
      then remove the service when the application is done using it.
        <programlisting>// create Map to hold required parameters
Map&lt;String,Object&gt; appCtx = new HashMap&lt;String,Object&gt;();
appCtx.put(UimaAsynchronousEngine.DD2SpringXsltFilePath, 
           System.getenv("UIMA_HOME") + "/bin/dd2spring.xsl");
appCtx.put(UimaAsynchronousEngine.SaxonClasspath, 
           "file:" + System.getenv("UIMA_HOME") + "/lib/saxon8.jar");
uimaAsEngine.deploy(service, appCtx);
    </programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
      
    </section>
    <!--======================================================-->    
    <!--                  Sample Code                         -->    
    <!--======================================================-->    

    <section id="ugr.ref.async.api.sample.code">
      <title>Sample Code</title>
      <para>See $UIMA_HOME/examples/src/org/apache/uima/examples/ee/RunRemoteAsyncAE.java
      </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
