<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/users_guide_and_reference/" >
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="sandbox.casEditor">
	<title>CAS Editor</title>

	<para>
		The
		<emphasis>CAS Editor</emphasis>
		is an annotation tool which supports manual and automatic
		annotation of CAS files. The CAS Editor can visualize and edit
		FeatureStructure, annotations can be viewed and edited directly
		on text. Currently only text based CAS are supported.

		<screenshot>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata width="700px" format="PNG"
						fileref="&imgroot;CasEditor.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>

	</para>

	<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.projects">
		<title>Projects</title>
		<para>
			The CAS Editor organizes all artifacts in a project. It is
			not possible to open artifacts which are located outside of
			the project.
		</para>

		<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.pojects.structure">
			<title>Project structure</title>

			<para>
				The project can be composed of these elements:

				<itemizedlist>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Typesystem</emphasis>
							The typesystem must be present for opening a
							CAS file or running a CAS processor.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Corpus folder</emphasis>
							A corpus folder is a collection of CAS
							files in the project. A project can have
							multiple corpus folders.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>CAS file</emphasis>
							The CAS itself, it must be located in a
							corpus folder and must end with ".xcas" to
							be recognized as a CAS file. Currently only
							xcas files are supported.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>CAS Processor folder</emphasis>
							A processor folder contains the Analysis
							Engine and Consumer Descriptor files. The
							CAS processor folder is also the data path
							for the processors. A project can have
							multiple processor folders.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>
								Analysis Engine Descriptor
							</emphasis>
							Configuration for an Analysis Engine which
							can be used to annotate CAS files in a
							corpus folder. To be recognized as Analysis
							Engine Descriptor the file must end with
							".ann" and must be placed in a processor folder.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Consumer Descriptor</emphasis>
							Configuration for a Consumer which can be
							fed with the CAS files in a corpus. To be
							recognized as Consumer Descriptor the file
							must end with ".con" and must be placed in a
							processor folder.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>

				These elements are shown differently than normal files
				and folders in the corpus explorer view. In addition to
				the listed elements a project can also contain files and
				folders e.g. for documentation.
				If one of these special elements contains an
				error a marker which describes the problem is
				added to the file.

				The corpus explorer with a project looks like this:

				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata width="257px" format="PNG"
								fileref="&imgroot;CorpusExplorer.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>
								Screenshot of corpus explorer
							</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</para>

		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.add_typesystem">
		<title>Add a typesystem</title>
		<para>
			Its strongly recommended to first add a valid typesystem to
			the project other functions are only available if the
			typesystem is present. Use copy and paste to import an
			existing typesystem. Editing of the typesystem is currently
			not supported inside the CAS Editor.

			<note>
				<para>
					If an external text editor is used to modify the
					typesystem close all editors inside the CAS Editor
					and run the refresh action.
				</para>
			</note>

			After the typesystem file is added make the CAS Editor aware
			of its existence. To do this open the Properties dialog for
			the project and then select the typesystem as shown here:

			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata width="400px" format="PNG"
							fileref="&imgroot;Properties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>

			Now the new type system element can be seen in the project
			tree of the corpus explorer.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.add_corpus">
		<title>Add corpus folder</title>
		<para>
			To add a corpus folder first create a new folder. Then open
			the Properties dialog and add the folder to the list of corpus
			folders. It than appears as corpus folder in the corpus
			explorer.

			The corpus explorer automatically hides all non CAS files in
			the corpus folder. The CAS files are organized in a flat
			hierarchy sub folders which contain CAS files are not
			recognized.
		</para>

	</section>

	<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.annotation_editor">
		<title>Annotation editor</title>
		<para>
			The annotation editor shows the text with annotations and
			provides different views to show aspects of the CAS.
		</para>

		<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.annotation_editor.editor">
			<title>Editor</title>
			<para>
				The editor has a edit mode. By default the editor only
				shows annotation of this type. Actions and views are
				sensitive to the edit mode. To switch the type of edit mode use the
				"Mode" menu in the editor context menu. The editor can
				also show other annotation which have not the type of
				the edit mode. For this use the "Show" menu in the
				context menu. The annotation renderer can be changed in
				the Properties dialog. After the change all editors
				should be re-opened.
			</para>
			<para>
				The editor automatically selects annotations near the
				cursor of the edit mode. This selection is then
				synchronized or displayed in other views.
			</para>
			<para>
				To create an annotation mark a piece of text and then
				press the enter key. The annotation now has the bounds
				of the selection and the type of the edit mode.
			</para>
			<para>
				To delete an annotation select it and press the delete
				key. Only annotations of the edit mode can be selected.
			</para>

			<para>

				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata width="500px" format="PNG"
								fileref="&imgroot;Editor.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>

			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.annotation_editor.outline">
			<title>Outline view</title>
			<para>
				The outline lists the annotations of the current edit
				mode of the editor. There are actions to increase or decrease
				the bounds of the selected annotation. There is also an
				action to merge all selected annotations.

				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata width="260px" format="PNG"
								fileref="&imgroot;Outline.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</para>
		</section>

		<section
			id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.annotation_editor.properties_view">
			<title>Properties View</title>
			<para>
				The Properties View shows details about the currently
				selected annotations or feature structures. It is possible
				to change primitive values in this view. Creation of
				feature structures is not possible.

				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata width="400px" format="PNG"
								fileref="&imgroot;PropertiesView.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>

			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.annotation_editor.fs_view">
			<title>FeatureStructure View</title>
			<para>
				The FeatureStructure View list all feature structures of
				a certain type. The type is selected in the type
				combobox.

				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata width="300px" format="PNG"
								fileref="&imgroot;FSView.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="ugr.tools.cas_editor.cas_processor_integration">
		<title>Cas processor integration</title>
		<para>
			The Analysis Engine can be run aginst a whole corpus or a
			few CAS files. To do this select a corpus or CAS files and
			then choose in the context menu the correct Analysis Engine.
			The filename of the Analysis Engine must end with ".ann"
			otherwise it is not recognized as an Analysis Engine.
		</para>

		<para>
			The Consumer can be fed with the CAS files inside a corpus.
			To do this select a corpus and then select the consumer in
			the context menu. To add a Consumer Descriptor paste a file
			into the processor folder. The filename must end with ".con"
			otherwise it is not recognized as consumer.

			<note>
				<para>
					If the CAS Consumer writes or modify files on the
					data path run the refresh action to synchronize the
					changes.
				</para>
			</note>
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
